Guide to the William [Bill] Stimson Collection of Donated Photographs of Pullman and WSU 1890s-1980s
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
William [Bill] Stimson Collection of Donated Photographs of Pullman and WSU
1890s-1980s
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
PC 141
Stimson, William, 1946-
2 Linear feet of Shelf Space 2 boxes Approximately 600 items
William L. Stimson compiled this collection of donated photographs for his published book Going to Washington State: A Century of Student Life. This collection consists of approximately 50 photographs of Pullman and Washington State University life, spanning the period from the 1890s to the 1980s. In addition to photographs, individuals also donated dance booklets and scrapbooks that illustrate early campus life in Pullman. Also included in this collection are a few photographs documenting California Native Americans, as well as photographs of Jayne Klyne McDonald, the second wife of nineteenth century Hudson Bay Company Chief Trader Archibald McDonald.
William L. Stimson compiled this collection of donated photographs for his published book Going to Washington State: A Century of Student Life. After graduating from Eastern Washington University, Stimson worked as a reporter for the Spokane Chronicle, United Press International and Reuters, and was editor of Spokane Magazine and Universe Magazine. He received his MA and PhD degrees in history from Washington State University, and is employed as a Professor of Journalism at Eastern Washington University.
This collection consists of approximately 50 photographs of Pullman and Washington State University life, spanning the period from the 1890s to the 1980s. The photographs were donated by Pullman residents and WSU alumni to aid in the creation of Bill Stimson’s book Going to Washington State: A Century of Student Life. In addition to photographs, individuals also donated dance booklets and scrapbooks that illustrate early campus life in Pullman. Also included in this collection are a few photographs documenting California Native Americans, as well as photographs of Jayne Klyne McDonald, the second wife of nineteenth century Hudson Bay Company Chief Trader Archibald McDonald.
The collection was received largely unordered. The collection consisted of photographs compiled by Stimson himelf as well as sets of photographs received by him as gifts from others. Many photographs are labeled with dates, but contain little or no description. The collection was processed at MASC into a loose chronological order, though each donor's gift was kept as an identified set to preserve its provenance, with the result being that the folders denote a series of overlapping dates rather than a strict chronological series. Donor names are noted on folders where applicable, but have not been included in this guide. Where it occurs, use of a photo in Going to Washington State is noted in this guide by the inclusion of dates and page numbers in parentheses.
This collection is open and available for research use.
This collection was received at Washington State University (WSU) Libraries' Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections (MASC) circa 1988-1989 from Bill Stimson, and accessioned in December, 2003 as UPC-0021.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Stimson, William, 1946- -- Archives; McDonald, Archibald, 1790-1853.; McDonald, Jayne Klyne
Washington State University -- Students.; Washington State University -- History.
Indians of North America -- California.
Colleges and Universities; Washington (State); Native Americans; California
- 1890s-1940s, Pullman and campus life used in Stimson’s Going to Washington State (1897 p. 10); (early 1900s p. 52); (1923/1973 p. 54); (1926 p. 75); (1927 p. 132); (1938 p. 57) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1890s-1940s, Pullman and campus life (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 1900-1920, Pullman and campus life (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1909, WSC athletics (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1918-1923, photographs and dance booklets (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 1920s campus scene (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 1935-1936, winter campus scenes, 1936 student strike (p. 99, p. 101, p. 103) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 1943, photograph of WSU swimmer Jennie May Thomas Harold (1943 p. 153) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 1950s-1980s, Pullman and campus life used in Stimson’s Going to Washington State (1951 p. 163); (1958 p. 185); (1962 p. 178); (1975 p. 248); (1977 p. 249); (1987 p. 274) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 1950s-1980s, Pullman and campus life (Box 1, Folder 10)
- 1954-1956, photographs of sorority life (p. 188) (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 1955-1958, photographs of Stevens Hall residents (p. 180, p. 183, p. 188, p. 191, p. 198) (Box 1, Folder 12)
- 1958-1962, Pullman and campus life (p. 201) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- 1920s-1930s dance booklets (1926 p. 90) (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Images of California Native Americans, associated with F.F. Latta and C. Relander (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Photographs of Jayne Klyne McDonald, second wife of nineteenth century Hudson Bay Company Chief Trader Archibald McDonald. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Stimson’s notes on photograph identification (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Cloth-bound scrapbook, loose photos, and letter of Cecil P. “Bud” Compau. 1919-1923 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Paper-bound scrapbook of Thelma J. Mahanes Brown (associated with folder #5 listed above). 1918-1923 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Going to Washington State. 2 photcopied proofs annotated with photo negative numbers. (Box 2, Folder 20-21)